现在已经看了正常情况的bin
so now that we've seen how the heap bins work during normal operation
以及chunk是如何缓存到不同bin的
and how chunks can flow between the different bins based on what is occurring
接下来看一下如何运用这些概念
let's take a look at how we can apply those concepts
来控制堆做我们想做的事情
to control the heap and start getting it to do what we want
在此之前
now before going any further
值得强调的是
it's worth emphasizing
堆利用严重依赖于libc版本
that heap exploits are heavily dependent on the libc version
在这个模块中
for this module
所有题目都适用于 libc 2.35
all of the challenges should be working with libc version 2.35
这是 ubuntu 22.04 lts 默认的libc版本
which is the latest version of libc that is used on ubuntu 22.04 lts
我记得libc 2.36版已经发布了
I do believe libc version 2.36 is out
但是我不打算在我们的练习题中用它
however I do not intend on using it for these challenges
不管出于什么原因
and for whatever reason
所有不使用 2.35版本的练习题
any of the challenges use a different version of libc than version 2.35
都会明示
the challenge will explicitly state it
libc版本很重要的原因是
now the reason that the libc version matters
不同版本的libc有不同的安全检查
is different versions of libc will have different validation checks or verification checks
所以漏洞利用的要求
and so the requirement
能做的，能改的
as far as what you can do and what you can change
每个版本的libc都不一样
is going to be different for every version of libc
一个很好的例子就是安全链接
a good example of this that we've seen is safe linking
安全链接只存在于现代libc的tcache和fast bins中
a safe linking is present on modern libc in tcache and fast bins
往前几个版本的libc
however if we were to go back a couple versions of libc
tcache 和 fast bins 中就没有安全检查
there is no safe linking on tcache or fast bins
再往前几个版本
and if we were to go a few versions back from there
甚至 tcache 都不存在
the tcache itself doesn't exist
但还有 fast bins
but we would still encounter fast bins
所以当在网上看到一些堆利用方法时
and so when you're looking online for heap exploitation
要注意这个利用方法是什么时期的
it's very important to be aware of how old is this exploit
它是针对什么版本的libc写的
what version of libc was this written against
因为有的针对fast bins的利用方法，可能没考虑 tcache
because there are fastbin exploits that used to work on libc that didn't have tcache
单是 tcache 的引入就改变了fast bin的利用方式
just the introduction of tcache changed the way that we interact with fast bin
还有些特性，不像tcache是新加的，而是弃用了
now sometimes features aren't added like tcache but actually removed
malloc hook就是一个很好的例子
a good example of this is the malloc hook symbol
它用于调试
which was meant for debugging purposes
你可以在这个hook符号处写入地址
it was a symbol where you could write an address
不管它指向哪里，malloc都会调用它
and whatever that address was would get called when malloc was called
这是一个很常见的攻击媒介
now this was such a common vector for exploitation
后来被从libc中删除了
that it was actually removed from libc entirely
所以如果你在网上发现一个依赖于malloc Hook的堆利用
and so if you find a heap exploit online that relies on malloc Hook
现在已经没用了
that doesn't exist anymore
需要好几个小时
now it would take several hours
才能过一遍libc 2.35中这些有名的堆利用
to go through all of the specific named heap exploits that exist in work in libc 2.35
它们都非常巧妙
all of them are very nuanced
都需要特定的设置
there's a very specific setup that is occurring
来创建相应堆漏洞环境
to create the situation inside of the heap where the exploit can occur
不会挨个演示
rather than do with that
我要讨论的是
I'm going to discuss
这些漏洞中使用的核心概念
some of the core concepts that are used in these exploits
所以在看这些漏洞时
so that when you look at them
你能推理出发生了什么
you can reason about what is occurring
并理解如何才能创建一个相同情景
and what you need to do to create the same scenario
然后复现你见到的利用方法
and replicate an exploit that you see
这些复杂堆利用中使用的许多概念
now many of the concepts that are used in these more complicated heap exploit
我们都见过
which are things that we've already seen
因为我们在之前 tcache 模块已经用过了
because we've done them in earlier heap modules with tcache
比如双重释放
things like creating a double free
你可能需要先使用双重释放
you may need to create a double free
来作为更复杂堆利用的引子
to even begin the exploitation process where a more complicated heap exploit
再比如 释放重用
or having a use after free
我们也见过了释放重用
we've seen use after free
许多有名的堆利用都需要释放重用才能实现
many of the name heap exploits require a use after free in order to pull them off
所以当你发现这些堆利用方法时
so when you look at these named heap exploits
他们需要一个释放重用
and you see that they need a use after free
你就应该考虑如何创建一个释放重用
you should be thinking how can I create a use after free primitive in the challenge
来复现这个技巧
to replicate that exploitation technique
如果无法创建释放重用
if I can't create a use after free
那么这个技巧就不适用
then that technique simply won't apply
在复杂堆利用中还存在另外两个核心概念
two other things that we've seen that also exist in more complicated heap exploitation
一是堆元数据破坏
is corrupting heap metadata
这个我们也见过
we've seen this where we overflow
从一个chunk中溢出到下一个
from one allocation into the next
破坏 tcache 的元数据
and corrupt tcache metadata
同样的它也存在于堆下层bins中
the same thing exists on the heap bins
只是元数据略有不同
except the metadata is slightly different
现在有前向和后向指针
because now we have those forward and backward pointers
是个双链表
it's now a doubly linked list
有不同的校验步骤
we have different verification steps
但原理还是一样的
but the same principle still exists
我们可以破坏内存和元数据
we can corrupt memory and corrupt that metadata
使堆行为失常或以意想不到的方式运行
to make the heap misbehave or act in an unintended manner
最后tcache中还有重叠分配
lastly in the module we saw overlapping allocations on the tcache
堆下层也存在重叠分配
overlapping allocations still exist with the heap heap
不过现在要创建重叠分配就有点困难了
now it's going to be a little bit more difficult to create an overlapping allocation
因为元数据更复杂
because the metadata is more complex
但是仍然可以创建重叠分配
but the overlapping allocation primitive can still be created
有一些堆利用技术
now there are exploitation techniques that exist on the heap heap
在 tcache 中没有
that didn't exist with tcache
其一是利用合并
and one of those things is taking advantage of consolidation
因为 tcache 不会合并
because tcache doesn't consolidate
那我们能利用合并做什么呢
so what can we do with consolidation
有几件事要记住
well there's a couple things to keep in mind
首先，不会放到 tcache 或 fast bin的chunk
first remember that chunks that do not go to tcache or fast bin
都会放到 unsorted bin
go to the unsorted bin
他们就像被延缓了截止日期
they're all kind of given that extra life
看看在这段时间能不能被从unsorted bin中捞出去
to see if the chunk can come back from the unsorted bin
我们可以控制unsorted bin
we can control what happens at the unsorted bin
申请一个large chunk
a correctly sized like a large malloc
能清空fast bins 和 unsorted bin，并且导致整合
can clear the fast bin and the unsorted bin and cause consolidation
同样，也可以让不想被合并的chunk不被合并
similarly maybe there is an allocation that I do not want to be consolidated
同时还要清空这2类bin
but I still want to clear out the bin
我们可以通过精心构建堆来实现
well we can do that by carefully crafting the heap
我们可以创建 卫兵chunk
such that we have a guard allocation
这个卫兵chunk只是为了防止目标chunk合并
and this guard allocation solely exists to prevent consolidation from occurring to another chunk
看一下工作原理
let's take a look at how that works
这里有一个玩具程序
all right so what I have here is a kind of toy program
它与前面堆模块的题目非常相似
very similar to what we've seen with some of the heap challenges in the earlier modules
这里很多堆题目都有这么一个循环
a lot of heap challenges follow this type of loop format
在这里可以调用 malloc、free、update、read、write之类的函数
where you can malloc free update read write that type of thing
对于现在的目标，我只需要malloc和free
now for our purposes all I need is malloc and free
我第一点说了，通过malloc一个large chunk
so my first claim was that with a correctly sized large malloc
可以清空fast bin和 unsorted bin，并导致fastbin整合
we can clear the fast bin or the unsorted bin and cause consolidation
看看我为此设计的代码
so let's look at my code for that
我总共要malloc 9次
so I'm going to malloc 9 times in total
先malloc 7次
I'm going to malloc 7 times
因为要把他们放到tcache中（填满链表）
because I intend to free them into the tcache
还要释放2次
I'm going to free an additional 2
要把他们放到 fast bin中
because I intend these to go to the fastbin
注意，我申请的大小很小
note that the size of my allocation is small
这样才能被放到fast bins中
so this is an allocation that is eligible to go to fast bins
我会输出PID，然后再开始交互
I'm going to print the PID and then go interactive
以便我们可以在GDB中查看
so that we can take a look at it in GDB
发生了什么
and see what's going on
先用gdb 附加目标进程
all right let's attach a GDB
首先我想查看一下 bins
so the first thing I want to look at is the bins
能看到我想要的实现了
and we see that what I intended to occur is what occurred
tcache中有7个chunk
we have seven chunks in the tcache
fast bin中有2个chunk
and we have two chunks here in the fast bin
能看到一个在27a0，另一个在27c0
we'll note that one of them is 27a0 and the other one is 27c0
这是他们在fast bin单链表中的顺序
now this is the order of them in this singly linked list of fastbin
还有一个命令可以查看chunk的物理位置
there's another command that I can use to look at the physical location of the chunks
并推断它们在内存中的位置
and reason about where they are in memory
那就是heap chunks
and that would be heap chunks
能看到在 27a0 处有个chunk
and we see here that there is a chunk 27a0
然后紧接着一个在27c0
and that immediately after that is 27c0
所以这两个块在内存中是紧挨着的
so these two chunks are right next to each other in physical memory
就算我不打印出这个
if I didn't print this out
我仍然可以这样推断
I could still reason that is the case
因为827a0加0x20等于827c0
because 827a0 plus hex 20 is 827c0
同样值得注意的是
it's also worth noting that
a0，C0，然后就是wilderness
we have a0 we have C0 and then we have the wilderness
最后这个chunk 很大
this last chunk here is very large
它表示当前存在于堆中的所有未分配数据
but this represents all of the unallocated data that exists currently in the heap
所以当我malloc一个large chunk 会发生什么呢
so what's going to occur when I malloc something large
当我malloc一个large chunk
well if I malloc something large
tcache 无法满足它
it is not going to be satisfied by the tcache
fast bin 也无法满足它
it's not going to be satisfied by fast bin
它也不会在small bins里找
it's not going to look in the small bin
因为是malloc的一个large chunk
because I'm mallocing something large
这就意味着我们要清空fast bins
and so that means that we're going to flush the fast bins
我们清空fast bins后
when we flush the fastbins
这些chunk将能被合并
these chunks will become eligible for consolidation
要记住：合并由PREV_INUSE 位决定
now remember that consolidation is determined by this previous in use bit
尽管27c0前面的，也就是27a0
and even though the previous of 27c0 which is 27a0
尽管它应该被标记为0
even though this one should be marked as previous not in use
但它还是被标记为1
it is marked as previous in use
这是因为它在fast bins里
this is because it's in the fastbins
所以当我们清空fast bins时
so whenever we flush the fast bins
27c0的PREV_INUSE位将被清0
27c0 the previous in use bit is going to be cleared
这使它能被合并
which then makes it eligible for consolidation
当它被合并时
and when that gets consolidated
它会和27a0合并，也就是向后合并
it will merge with 27a0 and it will consolidate backwards
但它也会向前合并进wilderness
but it can also consolidate forward into the wilderness
所以我们会看到所有这些chunk突然变成了一个
and so what we'll see is  all of these chunks here will suddenly become one
现在malloc一个large chunk
so let's malloc something large
然后看一下 heap chunks
and then take a look at heap chunks
发生了什么?
and what happened
我们看到了
well we saw
之前说的，所有这些会合并成一个
I claimed that all of these would merge together into one
确实是这样
and they did
这发生在malloc返回之前
they did that before we returned an answer to this malloc
他们合并成了一个在27a0处的巨大chunk
so we merged it all together into one giant chunk starting at 27a0
然后我们该满足malloc请求了
then we had to satisfy that malloc
我们从这个巨大chunk中分出2000B并返回
and so we had this giant chunk  and we broke off 2000 bytes and returned it
但这2000字节是从哪里开始的呢
but where did those 2000 bytes begin
它们从827a0开始
they began at 827a0
我们看到这个malloc返回的地址
and so we see the address that was returned by this malloc
与此处malloc返回的地址相同
is the same as the address that was returned by this malloc
尽管申请的尺寸大不相同
despite the sizes being drastically different
这样我们就可以导致整合发生
and so we can cause consolidation to occur
同样，也可以在unsorted bin中实现类似效果
and you can do a similar thing with the unsorted bin
malloc的值要比unsorted bin里的chunk大
you would malloc something that is larger than the values in the unsorted bin
这样会排完整个unsorted bin
and it would sort the unsorted bin
可以针对unsorted bin整点创新
now you can get a little bit creative here with the unsorted bin
因为如果你在unsorted bin中放入递增的chunk
because if you strategically place increasing values into the unsorted bin
比如把0x2000, 0x3000, 0x4000大小的放进unsorted bin
like let's say we put 0x2000 then 0x3000 then 0x4000 into the unsorted bin
然后malloc 一个0x3000的
and then I put in a malloc request for hex 3000
会发生什么呢
what's going to happen
先会看这个0x2000的chunk
well it's going to look at the Hex 2000
这个显然不满足0x3000
and say this is unsatisfactory
0x2000里分不出一个0x3000的chunk
I can't make 3000 out of 2000
它会把这个0x2000B的chunk放到large bin
and so it would sort the 2000 byte chunk
然后再看这个0x3000B的chunk
then it would grab and look at the 3000 byte chunk
能分出一个0x3000B的chunk吗
and say can I make a 3000 byte chunk out of 3000 bytes
可以的，这正是需要的
well the answer is yes this is exactly what I need
然后停止排序
and so it would stop sorting
并返回0x3000B的chunk
and return the 3000 byte chunk
不会再去看0x4000B的chunk
4000 byte chunk doesn't even get looked at
它依旧放在unsorted bin里
it's still sitting in the unsorted bin
所以你对unsorted bin有多少控制取决于
and so with the unsorted bin you have a bit more control depending upon
你对chunk大小
how much influence you have on the size of the chunks
以及他们在unsorted bin排序时的顺序有多少影响
and the order of them in the unsorted bin as far as flushing them out
要说的第二点是
now my second claim here is that conversely
你可以选定一个chunk，阻止它被合并
you can choose to hold an allocation and prevent consolidation
可以不改变chunk个数实现这个
now I could do this with the same number of chunks
但我觉得如果稍微修改一下，会更容易理解
but I feel that it's easier to understand if I slightly modify one in a clear manner
第一点和第二点的差异很小
so the difference here between 1 and 2 is pretty small
这里我依旧先申请7个大小为8的chunk
we see here I'm still mallocing 7 instances of size 8
再申请2个，用于填充fast bin
I'm then going to malloc 2 that I intend to put into fast bin
我再多申请一个
and I'm going to malloc 1 more
这多出来的一个
and this 1 more is there to serve as like a
我称之为合并卫士
consolidation guard is what I'm going to call it
先释放头7个
we're going to free the first 7
他们会放到tcache
so that we fill the tcache
然后释放下标为7的chunk
I'm then going to free index 7
我不释放下标为8的
I'm not going to free 8
再释放下标为9的
and I am going to free 9
启动程序
so let's run this
并用GDB附加进程
and attach GDB to it
检查一下bins
if we look at the bins
这看起来与前面的例子非常相似
this looks very similar to what we've had in the prior example
有7个chunk被释放到tcache中
I have 7 chunks freed into the tcache
fast bin中有2个
I have 2 chunks here in fast bin
有什么不同？这个卫士有什么用
so what is different what did this guard do
查看一下heap chunks
well let's look at heap chunks
现在fastbin里有两个元素
now I have two entries in fastbin
分别在 7a0 和 7e0
I have 7a0 and I have 7e0
这里是7a0
well here 7a0
这里是7e0
and here 7e0
卫士在 7c0 处
so my guard chunk was this one right here ending in 7c0
那么现在会发生什么呢
so what will happen now
它处于fastbin里的2个chunk之间
and it's sitting in between the two entries in fast bin
会发生什么呢
so what will happen now
如果我malloc一个large chunk
if I would malloc something large
还是会触发fast bins整合
well we would still flush the fast bin like that occurs no matter what
但当fast bins整合时
but when we flush the fast bin
对这些chunk的处理方式是不同的
we have to treat each one of these chunks differently
对于在7e0的chunk
so 7E0 this chunk here
它的PREV_INUSE位不变
its previous in use bit will not change
因为卫士还没free
because the guard is still allocated
它不在 fast bin中
this isn't in fast bin
当这个7e0处的chunk能被合并后
so then when this chunk becomes available
他可能会向前合并到wilderness中
it may consolidate forward into the wilderness
这种情况仍有可能发生
that could still occur
但它不能向后合并
but it can't consolidate backwards
那对于7a0处的chunk呢
now what's going to happen with 7a0
就是这个在fast bin里的chunk
which is this chunk right here that's in fast bin
对于7a0处chunk的PREV_INUSE位
well 7a0 it's previous in use bit
它会改变吗?
will it change
并不会
well the answer is no
它后面的是什么？780
what's behind it 780
780的chunk在某处使用着
780 is in use somewhere
所以清理fast bin时，7a0的PREV_INUSE不会变
so that's not going to change when we flush the fast bin
所以我们会看到7e0处的chunk
so what we would expect to see is 7E0 which is this chunk right here
会向前合并
will consolidate forward
7a0处的chunk则不会发生合并
7a0 is not eligible for consolidation
那这个chunk会放到哪里呢
so where does this chunk go
先看一下它的大小
well how big is it
chunk大小为0x20
this is a chunk of size hex 20
所以排序时
so if we had to sort this chunk and put it somewhere
它会被放到 small bins中
it should end up in the small bin
所以我预计7a0会放到small bins
so I am expecting to see 7a0 go to the small bins
我们malloc一个large chunk试试
let's perform the large allocation
看看之后堆是什么样的
and see how that influenced the heap
看一下bins
looking at the bins
能看到确实如预期的，fastbin被清空了
I do see that fast bins was flushed which we knew was going to happen
不同之处在于，7a0现在在small bins
the difference is 7a0 is now here in the small bins
能看到它现在有前向和后向指针
and we see that it has a forward pointer and a backward pointer now
因为它现在在small bins里
because now it is in the small bins
所以它是双链表的一部分
and so it is part of a doubly linked list
刚刚讨论的其它chunk呢
well what happened to the other chunk that we are talking about
原来那个 7e0 呢
what was that one 7e0
找不到了
well I don't see 7e0 here
为什么
why
因为 7e0已经合并到 wilderness中了
well 7e0 consolidated forward with the wilderness
然后是一个可以从中取2000B的地址
and then was the location that a 2000 byte chunk could be built from
嗯，7e0向前合并了
and so it consolidated forward
接着是一个2000B chunk的起始地址
and then that was the chunk from which a 2000 byte chunk began
所以原来的7e0和现在2000B的chunk地址相同
and so it began at that same spot
然后为了完整
and then just for completeness sake here
再来看一下 heap chunks
we can look at heap chunks again
能看到什么
and what do we see here
7a0在small bins中
7a0 is in the small bins
7a0在这里
there is 7a0
但有什么变了
but what changed here
当7a0从fast bins移到small bins后
well 7a0 when it moved from the fast bins to the small bins
显然它依旧未被使用
it is clearly not in use
所以内存中挨着它的chunk
and so the chunk that immediately follows in physical memory
紧跟着7a0的，也就是7c0
that immediately follows 7a0 which is 7c0
7c0的PREV_INUSE位已经被清0了
now has its previous in use bit cleared
这表明7a0可以被合并
and so this indicates that 7a0 is eligible for consolidation
然而，它不能向前合并
however it can't consolidate forward
对，因为这个卫士
right because of the guard
这是我们的合并卫士
this is our guard allocation
所以它不能向前合并
and so it can't consolidate forward into that
因为程序还在使用它
because the program still has it
它也不能向后合并 780
and it can't consolidate backwards into 780 either
为什么不能合并780
why can't it go backwards into 780
因为780目前被tcache占用
well it can't go into 780 because 780 is currently held by tcache
tcache使用相同的方法
and tcache performs that same kind of a trick
通过不清除PREV_INUSE位，防止合并
where the previous in use bit is not clear to prevent consolidation
所以现在7a0不能向后合并
and so right now 7a0 can't consolidate backwards
它也不能向前合并
and it can't consolidate forwards
所以它只能被放到small bins中
which is why it is now a small chunk in the small bin
我们可以根据对这些机制的了解来控制他们
and we are able to control that based upon our knowledge of how these mechanisms work
现在除了利用整合
now in addition to working with consolidation or making consolidation work with us
还可以在不同bin中转移chunk
we can also move chunks between the bins
现在看过了大概是如何清空fast bin
now we already saw kind of flushing the fast bin out
以及合并的过程
and how that works with consolidation
我们也可在unsorted bin中做类似的事
but we could also do something similar with the unsorted bin
事实上，我们对unsorted bin有更强的控制
in fact we have more control with the unsorted bin
因为unsorted bin是有条件性的清理chunk
because the unsorted bin is conditionally flushed
可以根据chunk大小来清理
and can be partially moved through depending upon the size of the chunks that are in it
如果malloc请求大小足够走到unsorted bin
remember that if a malloc call is large enough to get to the unsorted bin
unsorted bin可能包含small或large chunk
the unsorted bin can contain small chunks or large chunks
unsorted bin中2类chunk都能放
it can contain both
unsorted bin的chunk处理方式是
and what the way that the unsorted bin is processed is a chunk is looked at
先取出bin中头一个chunk
grab the first chunk that's in the bin
如果这个chunk小于需要的大小
if the chunk is too small for what we need
那就按类别放到对应的bin中
then we sort it and we place it in the correct bin
可能会把它放到small bins中
so we could place it in the small bins
可能会把它放到large bins中
we could place it in the large bins
总之会放到它该在的位置
but we put it where it needs to go
然后我们取出下一chunk
then we grab the next chunk
如果chunk正好是我们需要的大小
if the chunk happens to be the exact size that we needed
那很好
that's great
就立即把它返回给malloc
we'll return that chunk to malloc right away
但如果chunk太大了
but if the chunk is too large
比我们需要的大
the chunk is larger than what we need
那么分配器会
then what the allocator can do is
立即分割这个unsorted bin中的chunk
the allocator will split that chunk right now while it's in the unsorted bin
返回给malloc所需的部分
it'll return the piece that is needed for malloc
并将剩下的（last_remainder_chunk）留在unsorted bin中
and will leave the remainder in the unsorted bin
所以unsorted bin中的chunk也能被分割
and so the unsorted bin is a location where chunks can also get split
这意味着可以通过unsorted bin创建更小的chunk
and this means that we can create smaller chunks via the unsorted bin
然后清理unsorted bin将创建的chunk放到目标位置
and then flush the unsorted bin to place those chunks where we want
也可以只清理部分unsorted bin
you can also partially go through the unsorted bin
如果unsorted bin中chunk大小是递增的话
if the unsorted bin has chunks in increasing size
假设它有大小为100 1000和10000的chunk
say it has a chunk of size 100 1000 and 10 000
如果我请求一个800B的chunk
if I request an 800 byte chunk
当先遇到它时，会整理这个100B的chunk
we would sort the 100 if we encounter that first
然后取出1000B的chunk
then we would take the thousand byte chunk
分割，并返回800B的chunk
split it off and return an 800 byte chunk
严谨的说是816B的chunk，如果请求大小为800B的话
well an 816 byte chunk if it was an 800 byte allocation
剩下的部分放在unsorted bin中
well we would put the remainder in the unsorted bin
不会去碰这个超大的10KB chunk
and the super giant 10 000 byte chunk would be untouched
找到需要的chunk后就不动unsorted bin了
because remember we only process the unsorted bin until we find what we need
因此可以构造malloc请求，只遍历部分unsorted bin
so it is possible to make malloc requests to partially go through the unsorted bin
你可以利用这一点
and you can use that to your advantage
我要说的最后一点
the last thing that I'll mention that
在讨论small bins时没讲
I don't think was included in the discussion on the small bin
在某些情况下
was in certain scenarios
small bins会利用被访问的机会，缓存tcache
the small bin will take advantage of the fact  that it is being accessed to load up the tcache
如果 tcache 有空位
so if the tcache is empty
但small bin中有chunk
but there are small chunks in a small bin
而且此时正在访问这个small bin
and you're accessing that small bin right now
分配器会做的就是
what the allocator will do is the allocator will reason
既然已经访问到这个small bin了
since we are already accessing this small bin
就好好利用一下这个机会
let's take advantage of the fact that we're here
从在访问的small bin中，取出最多7个chunk，放到tcache
to load up the tcache with up to 7 small chunks from that specific size bin that is being accessed
我们可以看看具体是如何工作的
and we can take a look at how that works
好的
all right so
这个例子和上一个非常相似
this example here is very similar to the previous one
只不过目标不是fast bins了
except instead of targeting the fast bin
这次目标是unsorted bin
I'm targeting the unsorted bin
先malloc 7次
and so I'm going to malloc seven times
目的是之后将他们释放到tcache
with the intent to freeing them into the tcache
再malloc一次，准备放到unsorted bin中
I'm going to malloc once targeting the unsorted
再申请一个卫士chunk用于阻止向前合并
and I'm going to malloc once more with a guard allocation to prevent forward consolidation
我该如何锁定unsorted bin
now how am I targeting the unsorted bin
嗯，我
well I am choosing that
选择一个够大的，fast bins放不下的chunk大小
by choosing a size that is large enough that it will not go into the fast bin
注意：0x80B大小以内的chunk都会放到fast bins中
remember chunks up to 0x80 bytes end up to the fast bin
128(加元数据16B)大于0x80
128 is larger than 88
所以等释放完他们时
so when these get freed
在tcache填满后，这个会放到unsorted bin
after the tcache this should go to the unsorted bin
等释放后
so that's getting freed then
用gdb附加到该进程，然后查看此时的堆状态
I'm going to attach and take a look at the state of the program at that point
能看到unsorted bin中有一个0x90B的chunk
and what we see here is we have a chunk of size hex 90 in the unsorted bin
为什么是0x90
why hex 90
0x90等于144
well hex 90 is 144
144等于128加16
144 is 128 plus 16
注意，chunk有16B的元数据
remember there's 16 bytes for the chunk metadata
继续执行会发生什么呢
so what's going to happen if I continue running from this point
接下来要怎么做
well what are we going to do
接下来要malloc 7次，用于填充tcache
we're going to malloc seven times targeting the tcache
再malloc一次
we're going to malloc once more
用于之后放入unsorted bin
with the intent of putting something in the unsorted bin
第九次malloc，用做卫士chunk防止向前合并
and I'm going to malloc in 9th time with a guard to prevent forward consolidation
当首次malloc时
well when this very first malloc occurs
它会被放到unsorted bin里
that is going to go to the unsorted bin
unsorted bin里有一个144B的chunk
and the unsorted bin has a 144 byte chunk here
它无法满足256B的malloc请求
which will be insufficient to satisfy this 256 byte malloc
所以会将其放到对应的bin
so that means that we will sort this chunk
这个chunk会放到small bins中
so this chunk should end up in the small bins
这会发生在第一次malloc时
and that's going to happen on this very first malloc
接着会执行后续malloc
then we're going to do the rest of the mallocs
再free 8次
and free 8 times
这将在unsorted bin中放一个272B的chunk
and that will place a 272 byte chunk in the unsorted
我们继续
so let's move forward
可以看到
and see that
额，没变化
what we see now is the exact same thing
因为没执行continue
because I didn't continue
现在能看到unsorted bin中有一个更大的chunk
okay what we see now is a larger chunk in the unsorted
有0x110B，也就是256B
that is 0x110 just 256
哦，搞错了。好了
oh no that's not right there we go
是272B，因为要加16
272 because it's 256 plus 16
这正是预计的效果
which is what we would expect
可以看到144B的chunk已经转移到small bins中了
and we saw that the 144 byte chunk was moved to the small bin
所以我们可以把它放进small bins中
so we were able to flush this into the small bins
同时保留unsorted bin中的其它chunk
while simultaneously placing something in the unsorted bin
不需要malloc一个巨大的chunk将unsorted bin清空
we didn't have to just malloc something very very large and flush them all out
还有另一个例子
so I have another example
这个例子是将small chunk放到unsorted bin
this is when we were putting something small in the unsorted
然后malloc large chunk的情况
and then mallocing something larger
如果我们反过来做会怎样
what happens when we do the reverse
这其实就是代码后半部分
so this is just the later half of that
这里将272B的chunk放入unsorted bin
we're going to put a 272 byte chunk into the unsorted
然后启用交互模式
and then go interactive
我们运行并附加gdb到进程
so let's run this and attach
看一下这里
and if we look here
在unsorted bin中确实有272B的chunk
we do have a 272 byte chunk in the unsorted
那malloc一个更小的chunk会怎样
so what's going to happen if I malloc something smaller
比如64字节
like 64 bytes
发生了一些有趣的事
well something interesting happens here
unsorted bin中还是有chunk
we still have something in the unsorted bin
只不过unsorted bin中是个比原来小的chunk
but the unsorted bin chunk is now smaller
现在大小是0xC0字节
it is 0xC0
但我没free任何chunk
but I didn't free anything
我只执行了malloc
all I did was malloc
那这里发生了什么呢
so what happened here
我们说过，在遍历unsorted bin时
well we said when we're going through the unsorted bin
如果chunk小了，我们就把它放到对应bin中
if the chunk is too small we sort it
如果chunk大了
but if the chunk is too big
我们会怎么做
what do we do
我们会选择这个chunk
well we can use this
只是我们不想返回chunk中多余的内存
except we don't want to return all of this extra space
能看到这个chunk起始地址是63e30
and so we see this chunk began at 63e30
返回了什么？63e30
what was returned 63e30
这里也能找到它
find that over here again
63e30
所以返回的chunk其实是从这个更大的chunk中切出来的
and so the allocation that was returned was cut out of that larger chunk right here
那么此时在unsorted bin中的
so then the thing that's in the unsorted bin
就是切剩下的半块chunk
is whatever was left after we cut out the allocation
整个过程是，从unsorted bin中取出这个chunk
so we picked up from the unsorted bin this chunk
然后发现，这个够大
and said yeah this is big enough
然后将他分成两份
and then we just broke it in two
这份是我们要的
and said here's the piece that we need right now
余下的就放在unsorted bin，以后处理
leave the remainder in the unsorted bin to deal with later
那我该怎么做呢
so what can I do from here
要是我malloc一个巨大的chunk
well if I malloc something very large
就可以将在unsorted bin中切剩下的
I can flush that remainder piece that was in the unsorted bin
放到small bins中
into the small bins
所以现在不知怎么的
and so now somehow
最终在small bins中有了一个0xc0大小的chunk
I've ended up with a chunk of size 0xc0 in the small bins
尽管唯一被释放的是一个0x110B的chunk
even though what the only thing that was freed into here was a chunk of size 0x110
所以你可以从unsorted bin中取出chunk
and so you can take chunks that are in the unsorted bin
切割，然后将剩下的从unsorted bin中清出
break them down and then flush out pieces of the unsorted bin
你能推出剩下chunk的地址
and you can know what address will be there for that size
如果知道原来chunk的地址
if I know the address of the original pointer up here
那么我就能知道
then I can know the address of
剩下的被放到small bin中的chunk的地址
the remaining piece that was broken off  and flushed into the small bin
还有一件能做的事
now the last thing that I claim we can do
是small chunk可以从small bins转移到tcache
is small chunks can move into the tcache from the small bin opportunistically
之前在small bin的课程中没有提到
now this is something that I didn't mention in the previous lecture about small bin
我不是很确定
I'm not entirely sure
可能有漏洞利用方法依靠这个机制
there's probably an exploit somewhere that uses this mechanism
但我现在没想到是哪个方法
but I'm not immediately aware of one
所以这里和之前有点不同
so what I'm going to do here is a little bit different
我要调用7次malloc
I'm going to malloc seven times
目的是以后释放到tcache中
with the intention of freeing it into the tcache
再调用两次malloc
I'm going to malloc twice more
瞄准small bins
targeting the small bins
如何瞄准small bins呢
how am I targeting small bins
先填满tcache
well I'm going to fill the tcache
还要确保这些chunk有卫士守护
I'm going to make sure that these allocations are guarded
不让他们合并
so they don't consolidate
然后将他们释放到unsorted bin中
I'm going to free them into the unsorted bin
最后malloc个大的，使unsorted bin处理里面的chunk
then I'm going to force the unsorted bin to get sorted by mallocing something large
这会导致unsorted bin中的这两个chunk被处理
and that will cause these two chunks that were in the unsorted bin to get sorted
放到small bins里
and get placed into the small bin
再调用一下input
then I have an input
我们来看几个阶段来校验一下
so let's take a look at a couple phases there to verify that is what's going on
所以现在我应该有两个chunk
so right now I should have two chunks
我们就在这里
we are right here
在unsorted bin里应该有2个chunk
I should have 2 chunks in the unsorted bin
能看到unsorted bin确实有2个chunk
and I do have two chunks in the unsorted bin
现在我要malloc个大的
so now I'm going to malloc something large
这能将他们从unsorted bin中转移到small bins里
which should flush them from the unsorted bin to the small bin
我们试一下
so let's do that
现在可以看到unsorted bin是空的
and now we see the unsorted bin is empty
而small bins里有两个chunk
and we have two chunks in the small bins
现在开始变得有趣
now this is where it gets interesting
我现在要清空tcache
what I'm going to do is I'm going to clear the tcache
malloc 7次来清空tcache
so I'm going to malloc 7 times to clear out the tcache
然后进入交互模式
and then we're going to go interactive
现在能看到tcache中有7个chunk
so we see that the tcache does have seven entries for the size that we are working with
如果现在检查一下 heap bins
and if we look at the bins right now
已经清空了tcache
we've cleared out the tcache
small bins里还有两个chunk
and we still have two in the small bins
small bins有2个这个大小的chunk
two chunks in the small bins for this size
现在我要再malloc一次
now what I want to do is I want to malloc just once
按直觉来说
now our intuition is
这个大小正好可以从small bins里取
well this is the correct size to come from the small bins
所以应该会返回small bins中第一个chunk
and so it should return the first chunk in the small bins
应该返回7bd0
it should return 7bd0
实际是这样吗?
is that what happens
它返回了另一个chunk
well it returned the other chunk
但依旧是返回了一个small bins中的chunk
but it still returned a chunk from the small bins
这和我们预计的一样
and so that is what we would expect
但是这里发生一些有趣的事情
but so something interesting is going to happen here
如果我们检查一下heap bins
if we take another look at the heap bins
small bins现在是空的
the small bins are now empty
small bins是空的
and the small bins are empty
因为这个7bd0现在在tcache中
because that 7 where is it 7bd 0 is now in the tcache
所以这里到底发生了什么
so what the heck happened here
事实证明
well it turns out
当small bins里有一个以上chunk
when there are more than one chunk in the small bins
且tcache还没满时
and the tcache is not full
当我们malloc时
when we malloc
分配器认出这种情况
the allocator reasons about this
发现有多余的small chunk可以放到tcache
and says I have extra small chunks that could go into the tcache
只要我们处理到这个small bin对应的链表
as long as we're already working with this small bin list
就会填充tcache
let's load up the tcache
这就是这里发生的事情
and so that's what happened here
我们malloc了一次
we mallocd once
small bins里有2个chunk
we had two things in the small bin
就在这里和这里
right here and here
我们malloc了一次
we malloc once
small bins中的一个chunk返回给了我们
one of those small bin values was returned to us
7ab0
另一个 7bd0
and the other one 7bd0
被放到了tcache中对应大小的链表
was placed inside the tcache for that size
故当用到small bins中的chunk
so the allocator will preload tcache
分配器会将该bin中其它chunk装到tcache
if it's already working with that size in the small bins
这很有趣
it's kind of interesting
还有几件事值得一提
there's a couple more things that are worth mentioning
虽然我不会演示它们
although I'm not going to demo them
但它们都与这个模块相关
but they're definitely relevant for this module
第一种是伪造chunk
the first is creating fake chunks
我们在tcache中见过
so we saw with tcache
我们可以覆盖next指针
that we could overwrite in next pointer
然后让tcache返回一个
and get the tcache heap to start returning values that
它本不会返回的地址值
it's not necessarily supposed to be able to do
可以在下层堆做类似的事
well you can do something similar with the heap heap
然而，这不再是简单地覆盖next指针
however it's not as simple as just overwriting a next pointer or
或者为了绕过安全链接
performing safelinking modification
做些异或操作，并用修改后的值覆盖next指针
doing some XOR and writing a modified address to a next pointer
因为这里的堆元数据有前向和后向指针
because remember the heap metadata has forward pointers and back pointers
而且会校验这些指针
and it has validation on those pointers
会校验size与下一个chunk的prev_size是否相等
and it has validation on the size with the next chunks previous size
这种校验约束了那种修改方法
and so there's these validation checks that constrain performing those type of modifications
但是如果你有一块拥有写权限的内存
however if you have a region of memory that you can write
你能牢牢控制住它
and you have full control over it
那么你可以精心伪造一块逼真的堆chunk
you can carefully craft a region of memory by writing data that looks like heap metadata
所以你可能要写入一个prev_size
so you'd have to write a previous size possibly
写一个size
you'd have to write a size
写一个前向指针
you'd have to write a forward pointer
还有向后指针
you'd have to write a backward pointer
也有可能要写入fd_nextsize和bk_nextsize
you may or may not need to write a forward and backward size pointer
这取决于你要利用的是堆的哪个部分
depending upon what part of the heap you're interacting with
可能有些也需要这些指针
there may be something that requires those pointers as well
反正你可以直接写内存
but you could just write out memory
来让它看起来像堆元数据
so that it looks like heap metadata
如果你可以破坏现有的chunk
then if you can corrupt existing heap chunks
你就能让堆误认为你给的内存
you can get the heap to interpret your little region of memory
是真正的chunk元数据
as if it were the metadata of a heap chunk
你能伪造chunk
you can create fake chunks
但你得能很熟练地
but you have to be very skillful in particular
伪造你要传给堆的内存空间
in how you craft that memory region that you're going to be passing to the heap
取决于你的所作所为
depending upon the specifics of what it is you're doing
以及你使用的内存区域
and what memory region you're working with
这可能导致堆被破坏
this can quickly result in a broken heap
而像GDB、GEF和pwndbg这类工具
where tools like GDB and GEF or pwndbg
也不一定能获取堆破坏的具体原因
will not necessarily be showing you correct information
当输出堆的调试信息时
when you start printing out that heap debug information
它可能会通过指针单向追溯链表
because it may try and follow the pointers in one direction
但因为你对堆的修改
but because of the way that you've manipulated the heap
必须从另一个方向遍历链表
you have to follow the pointers in a different direction
才能发现哪里有问题
reason about what's going on
所以需要在gdb中打印内存
and so you'll start needing to print out memory regions in GDB
查看原始字节
and looking at the raw bytes
才能了解实际问题
to reason about what is actually going on with the metadata
所以这是一种利用方法
so this is something that you can do
但可能非常容易破坏堆
but you can quickly end up with a broken heap and
并见到第一节课中看到的错误信息
those corruption errors that I warned about in the first lecture
与伪造chunk类似的
now similar to creating fake chunks right
伪造chunk是伪造了chunk的全部元数据
creating a fake chunk is where you're trying to emulate the entire chunk metadata
你要尽量做到合理
and you're trying to do it reasonably faithful
但也可以粗糙的伪造chunk
it is possible to simply take a memory region
够通过检查就行
and try and craft it to just past the validation steps
尝试通过检查
and you're just trying to pass the validation steps
仅为了获取一个基础利用方法
so that you can get one specific exploitation primitive
比如创建个假chunk，正好得到了一个任意读
like I just happen to be able to get an arbitrary read by creating a fake chunk
创建的还不是一个完整的chunk
that isn't a fully working fake chunk
但已经足够
but it's a fake chunk that works just enough
获取一个任意的指针，进行任意读写
so that I get an arbitrary pointer an arbitrary read an arbitrary write
得到了些可以用于后续攻击的，基础利用方法
I get some type of primitive that I can then work with
记住一点
just keep in mind that
你对堆的篡改行为越多
the more you're doing this like breaking behavior of the heap
就越容易导致崩溃
the closer you are to just utterly crashing
上一个模块中，我们获得了些基础利用方法
in the previous module where we were creating exploitation primitives
我们利用的是tcache
we were working with tcache
tcache很好，因为
and tcache is great in the sense that
如果我破坏了tcache，大不了重连一次
if I break the tcache I can always connect again
重开一个线程就获得了一个新的tcache
and have a fresh thread and I have a fresh tcache right
但在利用下层堆时就不一样了
well that isn't the case once you go past the tcache into the heap heap
进程中所有线程都用的同样的下层堆
the heap heap is the same heap for all threads in the process
所以这种能快速重置的按钮就不存在了
so you don't have like this quick reset button that you can just hit
这让我们回到了原点
and so this kind of brings us full circle
现在我们回过头来看看这个unlink_chunk函数
and so now we're back in looking at this unlink_chunk function
这是第一节课的内容
that was back in the first lecture
如果我们看看这些校验步骤
and if we look at these validation steps
这里有几种不同类型的校验
there's a couple different types of validations that are occurring
这是第一个校验
there's this first validation
它检查当前要从链表删除的chunk大小
which is looking at is the chunk size of the current chunk that's being unlinked
是否等于下一个chunk的prev_size
equal to the previous size of the next chunk
这和bins、链表、指针没有任何关系
now this has nothing to do with bins and lists and the pointers
关注的只是内存中的下一个chunk
this is about the next chunk in memory
内存中的实际地址
the actual location in memory
如果我们看一下next_chunk函数
and so if we look at this next_chunk function
我们是如何知道内存中下一个chunk的地址的？
how do we know where the next chunk is in memory
先取指向当前chunk的指针
well we take the pointer which is where we're at
然后加上当前chunk大小
and we add our size
当前chunk结尾处的地址
whatever is at the end of the current chunk
就是下一chunk的起始地址
is the beginning of the next chunk
堆就是这样定义它的
because that's how the heap is defined
所以这就是下一个chunk
and so that is the next chunk
下一个chunk的prev_size最好
and the next chunk better have a previous size
和声称的当前chunk大小相等
that matches what I claim my size is
这是关于内存相邻的校验
and so this is about locality in memory
第二个校验
this second check this validation step
是关于双链表的
this is about the doubly linked list
它检查前一个chunk的后向指针是否等于自己
it does the back pointer of my forward pointer equal me
然后检查后一个chunk的前向指针是否等于自己
and does the forward pointer of my back pointer equal me
听起来好像无法通过这个校验
that sounds like something that you wouldn't be able to satisfy or to pass this validation step
但它实际上要求了什么
but what is it really asking for
它实际是要某处指针的值是当前chunk的地址
it's asking for a pointer where a specific offset is the address of the chunk
还有在另一处的指针的值也要是当前chunk地址
and then another pointer where the address at a specific offset is the address of the chunk
这些前向后向指针
now these pointers forward and back
如果我们能控制他们
if we have control over them
他们不一定非得指向一个合法的chunk
these don't necessarily have to point to valid chunks
只要指向要卸载的chunk地址就行
they just have to point somewhere where the offset is the address of the chunk I'm trying to unlink
所以要满足这个要求是有可能的
and it is possible to satisfy that constraint
这些是局部的
again these are about locality
所以当我们说下一个和上一个chunk时
so when we say next chunk or previous chunk
说的时内存中相邻的上下
we're talking about where in memory
当我们说前向和后向指针时
when we're talking about forward and backward pointers
说的是bin链表中的前后
we're talking about the list of the bins
所以我们可以找到内存中的下一个chunk
so we said that we can find the next physical chunk
只需要将当前chunk的地址加上chunk大小
by taking the address of the current chunk and adding the chunk size
那我们能找到上一个chunk吗
well can we find the previous chunk
上一个chunk地址等于当前chunk地址减去prev_size
the previous chunk is defined as the beginning of the current chunk minus the previous size
但请记住，prev_size有效的前提是
but remember the previous size is only valid
上一个chunk没在使用中
if the previous chunk is not in use
它得是空闲的
if it's currently free
那我们如何知道它是否是空闲的
and how do we know if the previous chunk is currently free
可以查看当前chunk大小的最低有效位
it is in the least significant bits of the current size of the current chunk size
我们在之前的模块中讲过
now we saw in earlier modules
如果能堆溢出
that if you have an overflow
你就可以覆盖chunk大小的值
you can overwrite that size value
当初是用来在tcache中创建重叠分配的
we did this to create some overlapping allocations with tcache chunks
在某些情景中，你能覆盖chunk的大小
so there are scenarios where you can overwrite the size of a chunk
如果找到溢出方法，溢出点要在chunk size前
that is in front of a chunk that you have write access to if you have some type of overflow
如果能覆盖chunk大小
and if I could overwrite the size
那肯定已经能覆盖prev_size了
I have already written past the previous size
所以在堆溢出情况
so in an overflow scenario
是可以设置或清除prev_inuse位
it is possible to set or clear the previous in use
以及prev_size的
and set or clear the previous size
由于prev_size决定了上一个chunk的位置
and since the previous size determines where the previous chunk is
故有2种不同方法操纵堆
there's two different ways to manipulate the heap
可以在内存中操纵它
you can manipulate it in physical space right here
只需修改size和prev_size
by messing with size and previous size
这将弄混chunk的起始和终止地址
and that's going to mess up where chunks begin and where chunks end
也可通过指针操纵它
you can also mess up the heap with pointers
就通过操纵这些前向后向指针
based on these forward and back pointers in manipulating them
有的chunk是从这些指针控制的地址中创建出来的（eg.从topchunk取）
so as such that a chunk is created from an address that is defined by these pointers
而不一定非得通过unlink_chunk函数
not specifically from the unlink_chunk function For Your Info
所以原则上通过操纵前向和后向指针
in principle by manipulating the forward and back pointers
也可以创建chunk
you can also create a chunk
故有2种不同堆攻击方法
and so there's two different avenues to kind of attack the heap
都能让堆行为异常并对你有利
and get the heap to misbehave in a manner that's beneficial to you
这些就是要考虑的全部内容
and so that is all stuff to think about
但真正的漏洞利用是什么样的呢
but what are the actual exploits
可以在这个网站找到漏洞利用
exploits can be found at this website
github.com/shellphish/how2heap
这个资源大概是我能为你们找到的最好的一个
this is probably the best single resource I can point you to
我在这节课开始的时候提到过
I mentioned at the beginning of this lecture that
堆漏洞严重依赖于libc版本
heap exploits are heavily dependent on libc versions
所以当人们在网上发布writeup时
and so when people do writeups and post them online
很容易就过时而无法使用
it's very easy to come across outdated or incorrect information
这个git仓库定期更新堆利用技巧
this repository is a regularly updated list of heap exploitation techniques
并根据libc版本管理并验证
that are organized sorted and verified by libc versions
这些漏洞利用是用C写的
these exploitation techniques are written in C
有可用的PoC
with working examples of the proof of concept
会在malloc、覆盖、溢出等之间
they print out kind of what the idea is between the mallocs and
输出解释性文本
the overwrites or overflows or what is going on
解释正在使用的基础利用方法
to try to explain the primitives that are at work
所以你可以运行它们
so you can run them
看看它在你的系统或你的libc上的实际效果
and see it in action that it does work on your system or on your libc
上面还有一个按钮可以让你运行交换式的web终端
it also has a button where you can run interactive web terminal
所以如果你没有Linux机器来尝试这些堆利用
so if you do not have a Linux box to do heap exploitation and playing around with these
你可以在交互式web shell上，尝试这里大多数的利用方法
you can run a lot of them on an interactive web shell
关于堆利用学习
on the topic of just generally learning about heap exploitation
你会遇到的一个问题是
one of the problems that you run into is
堆利用方法在其它libc版本的效果
you want to see how exploits work on other versions of libc
这个git仓库：glibc-all-in-one
this repository here glibc-all-in-one
提供了一个非常方便的工具
provides a pretty handy tool that
可以直接告诉它要下载2.32版本的libc
you can just say download libc version 2.32
它就会帮你下载
and it will go out and fetch it for you
构建，编译，并确保它可以正常运行
build it compile it and make sure that it's good to go
如果你对堆利用感兴趣
so if you are interested in heap exploitation
您肯定希望手边有多个版本的libc
you'll definitely want to have more than one version of libc handy
它是获取多版本libc的好工具
and this is a great tool to retrieve them
总结一下
so in conclusion here
会用到的堆利用方法
the heap exploits that we are going to be working with
都能在shellphish/how2heap中找到
will be found in shellphish/how2heap
就是这个git仓库
and this is the repository
能看到一系列的堆利用技术
and so we see there is a list of exploitation techniques
这是对它们的描述
there's a description of them
支持的最新libc版本
what is the latest libc version
是否有对应补丁
was it patched
有没有使用了这个漏洞利用方法的CTF题目
are there examples of CTF challenges that use this exploit
但对于本课程，我们将使用libc 2.35
but for this class we're going to be on libc version 2.35
这些是在libc 2.35上可用的利用方法
so these are the exploitation techniques that work on libc 2.35
有很多
there's a number of them
他们都依赖一些基础利用方法
and they all require some type of primitive
我们打开一个
and so if we were to open one
查看一下示例代码
and take a look the example code
可能假设目标程序存在双重释放
may assume that you have for instance a double free
可能假设有缓冲区溢出
where it may assume you have a buffer overflow
可能假设有释放重用UAF
it may assume that you have a use after free
即有chunk被free后
that a chunk gets freed
你还能对其写入，进而修改元数据
and you can still write to it to modify the metadata
所以要考虑这些利用方法依赖哪些基础方法
and so you need to be thinking about what primitives do these exploits require
还有这些利用方法能提供哪些新利用效果
and then what primitives does this exploit grant me
因为这些利用方法
because what these techniques do
能将你提供的基础利用方法
is they take something that you have
比如重叠分配
like overlapping allocations
转换成一个任意读或任意写
and turns it into an arbitrary read or an arbitrary write
因此，堆利用就变成了将基础利用方法
and so heap exploitation becomes about turning primitives
不断转换成另一种利用方法
into other primitives into other primitives
直到你最终达成你的目标
until you ultimately accomplish what it is that you need
所以想要完成这个模块
so to be successful in this module
你需要关注这个git仓库
you will need to pay attention to this repository right here
因为这将是理解堆利用的最佳资源
because that is going to be your best resource  for understanding what you can do with heap exploitation